#### **CURRICULUM VITAE**

I'm originally from Los Angeles, California and for the past 10 years I've been teaching English as a Foreign Language in Istanbul. This past summer I moved to Bury St. Edmunds with my family, and have subsequently chosen to pursue a new career in development. To facilitate this and ensure that my knowledge is up to date, I have recently graduated from a coding Traineeship as a full stack developer including completing 2 real-world projects successfully to specification using a wide range of programming languages. I feel development is an excellent fit for me due to my interest in technology and natural inclination to problem solving. I work well in a team environment but am also self-disciplined and can easily work independently as well. I consistently maintain a positive mental attitude towards tackling issues, and am always eager to pick up new skills as I work. I am committed to establishing a career in development as I see myself in the industry for the long term.

### **PERSONAL DETAILS**

NAME: Ernesto Estrada

**RESIDES**: Bury St Edmunds, Suffolk

**CONTACT DETAILS:** (M) 07470 693122

(E) ernesto@ernestoestrada.co.uk(W) https://ernestoestrada.co.uk/(GH) https://github.com/Ernie1812

CODING TRAINEESHIP IT Career Switch Ltd

Coding Traineeship – Full stack developer

1-year program

During the traineeship I had to demonstrate a very competent level of the following programming languages and technical skills

- HTML5, CSS3, JavaScript
- PHP, Java, SQL
- Python, C#, React
- Git, API

I have recently passed my Microsoft 98-383: Introduction to Programming Using HTML and CSS. More information on this certification can be found at: https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/learn/certifications/exams/98-383

### **DEVELOPMENT EXPERIENCE:**

Below are the two briefs of development projects I successfully completed with IT Career Switch which can be found in my bio: <a href="https://ernestoestrada.co.uk/">https://ernestoestrada.co.uk/</a>

### Portfolio Project #1: "Gazetteer"

The specification was to reply to a website specification for a map-based app to provide information on countries — with a focus on a "mobile first" development. Preferably using a framework, to then develop HTML, CSS and JavaScript with JQuery modules that use PHP server-based components to source data from third party APIs (Geonames, OpenWeather). The solution is assessed on its delivery to specification, functionality, and usability.

#### Portfolio Project #2: "Company Directory"

A more rigorous reply to this specification was required as a user requirements document was needed to be prepared which, when signed off, triggers the release of SQL allowing to develop a "mobile-first" application to maintain a company personnel database (MySQL). Sign off is only achieved upon the student supplying an independently witnessed document providing confirmation of the system's ability to perform error free.

### **CAREER HISTORY:**

#### Oct 2020 - Present

#### Career break

- I have spent this time as a stay-at-home father to my two young children.
- I have also invested time in studying and obtaining my Microsoft certification and completing projects to gain practical experience with the coding languages that I have studied.
- I am now immediately available for any roles in the development field.

### Sep 2015 – Sep 2020 POSITION HELD:

# FMV Işık Okulları, Turkey EFL English Teacher

- Worked as an English Skills teacher for Grades 5, 6, and 7 with a strong focus on reading, writing and speaking
- Developed and implemented 7th Grade English Skills curriculum in collaboration with department head and colleagues
- Collaborated in the development and implementation of Grades 5 and 6
   English Skills curriculum

### Jan 2014 – Aug 2015 POSITION HELD:

# Bilfen İlkokulu ve Ortaokulu, Turkey EFL English Teacher

- Worked as a language arts teacher for Grades 4, 5 and 7 with a strong focus on speaking and reading
- Taught 28+ lesson hours a week with frequent additional responsibilities on Saturday
- Solidified skills in classroom and behavioural management
- Responsible for collaborative lesson preparation
- Liaised with parents to discuss student progress and performance

## Sep 2012 – Jan 2014 POSITION HELD:

# Modafen İlköğretim ve Lise, Turkey EFL English Teacher

- Worked as a language arts teacher with a focus on speaking and reading
- Experienced in teaching students from Grade 4 to Grade 6
- Developed and implemented differentiation techniques in order to cater for the varying levels of English in one cohort
- Prepared students for Cambridge English proficiency exams: Starters, Movers, Flyers, KET, PET and FCE

### Sep 2011 – Jul 2012 POSITION HELD:

# Özel Mürüvvet Evyap Okulları, Turkey EFL English Teacher

- Taught general English (elementary to upper-intermediate) to high school students from Grade 9 to Grade 12
- Skilled at classroom and behaviour management
- Responsible for the assessment of student performance

Aug 2010 – Oct 2011 POSITION HELD:

### Just English Language School, Turkey EFL English Teacher

- Taught TOEFL exam skills and general English (elementary to upperintermediate)
- Responsible for lesson planning and the implementation of the program

Oct 2007 – Apr 2010 POSITION HELD:

## Just English Language School, Turkey Policy Associate

- Researched state and federal military veterans policy and presented analytical reviews on top findings to local, state and federal lawmakers
- Conducted trainings to large (over 50 persons) and small groups of community-based social welfare providers, clinical staff and other key stakeholders regarding cultural competency, the veterans' social welfare system, and veteran homelessness

Feb 2006 – Sep 2007 POSITION HELD:

Americano Restaurant, USA Waiter

Sep 2004 – Jan 2006 POSITION HELD:

P.F. Chang's China Bistro, USA Waiter

Jul 2003 – Sep 2004 POSITION HELD: Elephant Bar Restaurant, USA Waiter

Jul 1999 – Aug 2003 POSITION HELD: United States Marine Corps
Non-commissioned Officer (Sergeant, M1A1 Abrams Tank Crewman)

- Supervised and performed all aspects of M1A1 Abrams tank operation and crew level maintenance
- Instructed and mentored eight Marines under supervision regarding job proficiency and personal conduct
- Supervised and conducted staff development training of 15 25 Marines in classroom and field environments

**EDUCATION**:

2010 International House Akcent, Czech Republic

Cambridge CELTA

2007 San Francisco State University, USA

BA (Hons) History